Well, the first thing you're going to notice is that I don't have a notebook open for you.
가장 먼저 눈에 띄는 건 펼쳐놓은 공책이 없다는 거죠
And that's because this time we're just going to be looking at code.
왜냐하면 이번엔 코드만 볼 거니까요
Uh, no notebooks for this recording.
녹음에 수첩은 안 돼요
For this video, we are going to look at the actual finally, the actual agent framework itself that
이 비디오에서 실제 finally를 살펴보겠습니다 우리가 작성하고 구축하고
we're writing that we've, that we've built, that we're going to run it in.
실행할 실제 에이전트 프레임워크요
And it sounds like something so fancy, but in fact, it's going to be incredibly simple.
아주 멋진 것 같지만 사실 아주 간단해요
And it's the reason why I didn't want to use an off the shelf kind of package, because I just wanted
이런 이유 때문에 제가 기성품 패키지를 사용하지 않는 겁니다
to show you that there's nothing more than connecting together, different llms and bits of Python code
보다 고급된 함수를 수행하기 위해 서로 연결하는 것 이상의 것은 없다는
to carry out a more advanced function.
걸 보여드리고 싶었어요
Now, typically when you talk about these sorts of agent frameworks, what you're looking for is you're
보통 이런 종류의 에이전트 프레임워크를 이야기할 때 데이터베이스
looking at something that can handle the database, uh, database connectivity, in our case to our
연결을 다룰 수 있는 무언가를 찾습니다 이 경우에는 크롬 데이터
Chrome data store memory.
스토어 메모리인데요
So we're going to want some sense of persistent memory.
지속적인 메모리 감각을 원하죠
Um, that can that can survive between different chats or of different instances, so we'll understand
채팅이나 인스턴스 사이에서 살아남을 수 있도록요 메모리가 어떻게 작동하는지
how memory is going to work.
이해할 수 있게요
And also stuff like logging I mentioned is sort of good, good practice to be able to understand what's
그리고 로깅 같은 것도 말씀드렸듯이 여러분 환경에서 무슨 일이 일어났는지 이해하는 데
happened in your environment.
좋은 연습이 되죠
And then there's also going to be some user interface concerns that we're going to want to build a Gradio
사용자 인터페이스 문제도 있을 겁니다 이 프레임워크를 사용할 수
UI that's going to be able to use this framework.
있는 그래디오 UI를 구축해야 하니까요
So it's going to have to to handle that.
그걸 처리해야 해요
But that last one we're going to get to in the next set of series.
마지막 것은 다음 시리즈에서 보여드릴게요. Get up
Uh, so for now we're going to look at our, at our framework.
지금은 프레임워크를 살펴볼 거예요
Just before that, a couple of things to point out.
그 전에 몇 가지 짚고 넘어갈 게 있어요
First of them, when we looked in our agents folder, we've looked at each of these different classes.
먼저 에이전트 폴더를 보면 각각의 다른 클래스를 보았었죠.
That represents a different unit of work.
그건 다른 업무를 상징하죠
And you'll notice that each of them were subclasses of agent.
모두 에이전트의 서브클래스인 게 보이시죠
Uh, and you may have wondered, what is that?
이게 뭔지 궁금하실 거예요
What is this agent that he's subclassing is there must be all sorts of functionality in there.
서브클래싱하는 에이전트가 무엇인지 모든 기능성 요소가 들어있는지를요
Well, actually, no, there's very little functionality in this superclass.
사실 이 슈퍼클래스엔 기능성이라곤 거의 없어요
Uh, it is actually just an abstract class.
그냥 추상 수업이에요
Uh, which is able to log a message.
메시지를 기록할 수 있죠
And the way that it logs a message is it does logging.info.
메시지를 기록하는 방법은 로깅을 하는 거죠 정보요
I imagine you're familiar.
잘 아실 거예요
You've used Python logging, probably.
파이썬 을 로깅한 적이 있을 거예요
And so you're pretty.
그래서 예쁘죠
Familiar that logging.info logs, uh, to to to wherever you set up a logger for, um.
로깅이 익숙하네요 벌목꾼이 있는 곳이면 어디든 정보를 얻을 수 있어요
And.
그리고요
The one thing that I'm doing that's a bit different here, um, is that I'm going to.
제가 여기서 하는 것 중 조금 다른 건 비트를 입힐 거예요
Add in the name of the subclass of the agent.
에이전트의 서브클래스 이름을 추가하세요
That's that's, uh, that's.
그건... 그건 말이죠
Actually, uh, sending this log message and we're going to give each one a color.
로그 메시지를 보낼 건데 각각 색깔을 지정할 거예요
So that we can see, uh, what which agent is doing what?
그러면 어떤 요원이 어떤 역할을 하는지 알 수 있죠
And for example, if I go back to, uh, or if I go to the specialist agent, you can see that it's
예를 들어, 다시 돌아가서, 전문 에이전트로 가보면, 이름이 있는 것을 볼
given itself a name.
수 있어요.
Of specialist agent.
특수 요원이죠
And its color is red, so that when it logs, it's going to.
색은 빨간색이라 통나무를 쌓을 때 이렇게 되죠
Appear in red.
빨간색으로요
And you can see that you might have noticed that I didn't do.
제가 안 한 걸 눈치챘을 거예요
Logging.info I did self dot log.
로깅을 했어요 셀프.로그를 했어요
And that's so that I can call the log message in the superclass.
슈퍼클래스에서 로그 메시지를 호출할 수 있어요
So you know, there's really nothing fancy to this agent superclass.
이 에이전트 슈퍼클래스는 화려한 게 없어요
It just meant that we could log consistently.
일관되게 로그인할 수 있었죠
You could equally well have just included that function in the different classes.
다른 클래스에도 똑같이 함수를 포함할 수 있었어요
Nothing particularly special about the agent.
그 요원은 특별할 게 없어요
All right.
좋아요
One other bit of groundwork to do is to show you this JSON file called memory JSON.
비트 워크 중 하나는 메모리 JSON 파일을 보여드리는 거예요
And it is a simple piece of JSON.
단순한 JSON 기능이죠
And if it didn't exist then then you'll see it will it will create it manually.
존재하지 않았다면 수동으로 생성하는 걸 보실 수 있어요
Let's open it with the editor, not with the fancy one, but with the normal editor.
편집기로 시작합시다 화려한 거 말고 일반 편집기로요
And this is what it looks like.
이렇게 생긴 거예요
It is a list.
목록 맞아요
You can see it's got a list on the outside of it, a list of JSON blobs.
바깥쪽에 목록이 있는 게 보이시죠 JSON blobs 목록이요
And each JSON blob is something which may look familiar to you.
각각의 JSON 덩어리는 여러분에게 익숙할 거예요
Do you recognize what it is?
뭔지 알겠어요?
Yes, it's of course, an opportunity object turned into JSON.
네, 기회 객체가 JSON으로 바뀐 거죠
It's got a deal which has a product description, price and URL, and then it has the estimate that's
제품 설명, 가격, URL 등의 정보가 있는 거래가 있고 모델에서 나온 추정값도
come from the model and it has a discount, which is quite simply this number minus this number.
있어요 할인 항목도 있는데 간단히 이 숫자에서 이 숫자를 빼죠
Oops.
이런, 미안해요
That number.
그 숫자요
Ha.
네
Uh, it's how much is this being offered at a discount to what we think it's really worth?
실제 가치로 추정할 때 얼마나 할인해 주나요?
So this memory has three deals that have been surfaced.
이 메모리에 세 건의 거래가 드러났어요
Uh, now, storing it in a JSON file like this is perhaps not the most industrial strength.
JSON 파일에 이렇게 저장하는 건 산업용 강도가 그리 높지 않아요
If that went into a database, then it's something that could handle multiple of these agent frameworks
데이터베이스로 간다면 실행 중인 다수의 에이전트 프레임워크를 처리할 수 있는 뭔가가 되겠죠
running.
하지만 에이전트 프레임워크는 한 번만 이 메모리에 입력할 수 있어요
work.
꼭 필요한 건 아니지만 크롬 도금 작업은 쉽죠
We've got a database hanging around already, so you could certainly take that as an exercise if you
데이터베이스가 이미 있으니 원하시면 그걸 연습으로 삼으세요
Um, that would certainly be a good, good production improvement to make.
생산성이 크게 향상될 거예요
But anyway, the time has come to look at the actual, uh, the, the framework itself, the agent framework.
어쨌든 이제 프레임워크 자체를 살펴볼 때가 됐어요 에이전트 프레임워크요
Uh, so let's do that right away.
그럼 바로 시작하죠
Um, and I want to make sure I bring up the right class so that I don't give too much away of what is
그리고 올바른 수업을 진행하고 싶어요 앞으로 있을 수업에 너무 많은 걸 알려주지
still to come.
않게요
Here it is.
여기 있네요
Deal agent framework.
거래 요원 프레임워크예요
Uh, okay.
네
So the, uh, agent framework, um, is something which, first of all, it sets up logging.
에이전트 프레임워크는 우선 로깅을 설정하는 거예요
This is something which is standard Python stuff that will make sure that when someone does logging.info,
이건 표준 파이썬 으로 누군가 로깅을 할 때 확실히 해두죠 get-turefo는 기본으로
um, it will get sent to standard out and it has some, some structure to it.
보내지고 몇 가지 구조가 있어요
So this is a sort of standard, uh, um, boilerplate Python stuff to make sure we log properly.
이건 표준 파이썬 문서예요 제대로 기록하기 위한 상용 문서요
And then this is the deal agent framework.
이건 거래 에이전트 프레임워크예요
It's got coded in it, the database, the thing that I accidentally left off a couple of times, uh,
데이터베이스에 코딩되어 있어요 제가 실수로 몇 번 놓친 거죠 메모리
so that's coded in here along with the name of the memory file.
파일 이름과 함께 여기에 코딩되어 있어요
When it starts up, it will begin logging.
불이 붙으면 로깅을 시작할 거예요
It will make a log message itself.
로그 메시지를 만들 거예요
It will load the env.
그럼 부럽죠
This is something that we, of course, always do in all of our Jupyter notebooks.
이건 우리가 모든 주피터 공책에 항상 쓰는 거예요
So this needs to do it now.
이제 이걸 써야 해요
It will, it will create or it will access the database.
데이터베이스를 생성하거나 접근할 거예요
Um, it will read in memory from that JSON file.
JSON 파일 메모리에서 읽을 거예요
Uh, it will get the products collection and it will then set the planning agent, uh, initializing
어, 제품 컬렉션을 받고 기획 에이전트를 설정해서 Get up을 해야 하는
it with the collection that it needs to look at.
컬렉션을 초기화하는 거죠
And then it will say, I'm ready.
그럼 준비가 됐다고 나오죠
This this method here read memory does exactly what it says on the tin.
이 메서드는 메모리를 읽는데 함석에 적힌 그대로를 해요
It, uh, you can see I haven't hard coded the name of the file.
파일 이름을 하드코딩하지 않은 걸 보실 수 있어요
Well done, well done.
정말 잘했어요
Me?
저요?
Uh, so it loads this in from JSON.
JSON에서 로드하는 거죠
If it doesn't already exist, then it just returns an empty one, which is completely fine, because
이미 존재하지 않는다면 빈 것을 반환합니다 함수도 있으니
there's also a function.
괜찮아요
A method here writes memory, which writes out these opportunities to, uh, the the memory file.
메서드는 메모리를 쓰고 메모리 파일에 이런 기회를 쓰는 거예요
There's a log, uh, a method here to send a log message with its own agent framework tag.
로그 메시지가 있어요 로그 메시지를 보내는 메서드죠 에이전트 프레임워크 태그와 함께요
Then there's a run method that actually kicks off the planning agent.
그리고 기획 에이전트를 시작하는 실행 메서드가 있어요
Uh, and uh, once it gets back a result, it says it calls self dot planner.
결과를 받으면 셀프 닷플래너를 호출해요
Plan that.
그렇게 해요
Of course, that's the big moment.
중요한 순간이죠
That's when we we actually set this thing going.
그때 이 작업을 시작하게 됐죠
And look it passes in its memory.
보세요 메모리로 지나가요
It passes in the memory of opportunities that it knows about.
자신이 아는 기회의 메모리를 지나쳐 가죠
So in that goes uh, and then it logs the results.
여기에 넣으면 결과를 기록해요
And if the result wasn't none, remember that the planner might return none if it doesn't find anything
그리고 0이 아니면 새로운 결과가 나오지 않으면 0을 반환할 수도 있다는 거 기억하세요
new.
하지만 실제 결과라면 메모리에 추가하고 메모리를 쓰고 결과를 반환하죠
And that is it.
그게 다예요
This last piece here is coming up in the UI to the next time, but for now, that is the end of the
마지막 부분은 UI 다음에 나올 겁니다 지금은 프레임워크의
framework.
끝이죠
So how do we run this framework?
이 프레임워크를 어떻게 실행하죠?
Well, we run it from the command line.
명령줄에서부터 실행하는 거죠
This is now for reals.
이제 진짜 시작이에요
This is no longer this is all Python code.
파이썬 으로만 된 코드죠
We're outside the Jupyter world and we're using this interface for convenience.
우린 주피터 세계 밖에 있고 편리함을 위해 인터페이스를 사용하죠
Really.
정말이에요
But you could be using VSCode or something like that.
하지만 VSCode나 그런 걸 사용할 수도 있죠
The way to run a terminal is we press the plus button here.
터미널을 작동하려면 플러스 버튼을 눌러요
We can also do it in JupyterLab and we can open a new terminal like this.
주피터랩에서도 이렇게 새 터미널을 열 수 있어요
This is a you can also, of course be doing this however you like to do it.
물론 여러분이 원하는 대로 할 수도 있어요
Um, it could be an anaconda prompt or it could be you could be using.
아나콘다 프롬프트일 수도 있고 여러분이 사용할 수도 있죠
If you're using a mac, then you can just bring up a new terminal window.
Mac을 사용한다면 새 터미널 창을 불러올 수 있어요
Um, but I am first going to have to activate my conda environment.
하지만 먼저 콘다 환경을 활성화해야 해요
Um, so I do conda activate LMS, uh, which will mean that as you're now very familiar, uh, my environment
콘다가 LMS를 활성화합니다 그 말은 여러분이 이제 아주 익숙해졌지만 제 환경이 베이스에서 LMS로
changes from base to LMS because I'm now in that Anaconda environment, and I really think that's it.
바뀝니다 지금 아나콘다 환경에 있으니까요 정말 그게 다인 것 같아요
I should now be able to say Python deal agent framework.
파이썬 딜 에이전트 프레임워크라고 할 수 있어야 해요
Spell it right.
철자를 맞춰요
Dot py.
닷 피요
And that should really be it.
그게 다일 거예요
There is one more thing I need to show you before I do that though.
그 전에 보여드릴 게 하나 더 있어요
I almost forgot just as well.
하마터면 잊을 뻔했네요
It's just this very last few lines here.
이 마지막 선만 남았어요
You might have been wondering what's going to happen if I do that, if I don't show you this.
제가 이걸 보여드리지 않으면 어떻게 될지 궁금하셨을 거예요
So the very end, we of course, make it clear that if this is being run from the command line so that
끝에서 명확히 해야 할 것은 명령줄에서 실행되어 이 파일이 메인이라면 인스턴스화하고
this file is main, then we instantiate, we create a new instance of deal agent framework.
거래 에이전트 프레임워크의 새 인스턴스를 생성해요
And we call this run method that we just looked at.
방금 본 실행 메서드죠
That's the little missing link there just to explain okay okay.
빠진 고리가 있네요 설명하자면요
With that.
저거로요
Now I should be able to run this.
이제 실행할 수 있어야 해요
Take a deep breath.
심호흡을 하세요
Let's do it.
시작하죠
A long pause while it thinks, huh?
생각할 시간이 길군요
All right.
좋아요
Let's see what's going on.
무슨 일인지 보죠
The agent framework says it's initializing.
프레임워크 말로는 초기화되고 있대요
The planning agent is initializing scanner.
계획 담당이 스캐너를 가동 중이에요
Agent becomes ready.
에이전트가 준비됐죠
The ensemble agent gets ready.
앙상블 에이전트가 준비 중이에요
So then it's a bit hard to see this.
그래서 비트를 보기가 좀 힘들어요
Read the specialist agent, which is connecting to modal, gets ready.
모달과 연관된 특수 요원이 준비 중이에요
And then the frontier model gets ready.
개척지 모델이 준비됐죠
It has to load in that sentence transformer.
그 문장에 변압기를 로드해야 해요
You can see it's happening there.
저기서 일어나는 일이 보이죠
And then the random forest agent gets ready as well.
그리고 임의의 숲 관리인도 준비를 하죠
And that's done.
다 됐어요
The ensemble is ready, the messenger is ready.
앙상블도 준비됐고 전달자도 준비됐어요
And everything in blue.
전부 파란색으로 칠하고요
Here it says Agent Framework is ready.
프레임워크 요원이 준비됐다고 나오네요
So it went through instantiating and creating all of our agents and setting them all up.
인스턴스화와 모든 에이전트를 생성하고 셋업하는 과정을 거쳤어요
They've loaded their model weights that they've the single one the specialist model has connected to
전문가용 모델에 맞는 무게추 하나만 실었어요
And they have now, um, all prepared themselves for action.
이제 다들 행동에 나설 준비가 됐어요
Model weights have been read in and it's kicked off a run.
모델 웨이트를 읽고 런을 시작하네요
The scanner agent you can see here, uh, received there's a there's an error there.
여기 보이는 스캐너 요원은 오류가 있다는 걸 받았어요
I'll improve that.
더 잘할게요
It's not printing the actual number of results.
실제 결과의 수는 출력하지 않아요
It's printing needs an F before it.
인쇄하기 전에 F가 필요해요
Uh, I will have fixed that before you see it.
보시기 전에 고쳐 놓을게요
Uh, so the scanner agent is making that call.
스캐너 요원이 판단하는 거죠
Um, and now the planning agent is pricing up the deal, and it's now sitting with modal while my machine
기획사에서 가격을 매기고 있고 제 기계가 예열되는 동안 수정을 기다리고
warms up.
있어요
Uh, but as they say on those cooking shows, uh, if you know what I mean, uh, you have those cooking
근데 요리 프로에서 보면 이런 말이 있잖아요 무슨 말인지 아시죠? 그런 프로 보면 오븐에
shows when they put the thing in the oven and they say, and here's the one that I put in earlier,
뭘 넣잖아요 제가 아까 넣은 건 이렇게 나오는데 그걸 오븐에서
and they pull that out of the oven.
꺼내요
I always think that's a devious trick when they do that.
그런 걸 할 때 보면 교활한 속임수 같아요
But you're going to have to trust me that I did just do this.
하지만 내가 방금 했다는 걸 믿어야 해요
I just kicked it off a few minutes ago and it ran over here, and that's where I left it, and it finished
몇 분 전에 발로 찼는데 이쪽으로 달려오더라고요 그래서 여기 뒀더니 일을 다
up its thing.
봤어요
And you can see that basically it for each of the five deals that returned, it made a series of calls
기본적으로 반환된 5개의 거래마다 모든 다양한 모델에 일련의 전화를
to all of the different models.
걸었어요
You can read through each of this.
하나씩 읽어 보세요
The ensemble model returns a number.
앙상블 모델은 숫자를 돌려줘요
Um, so we should we should work back.
그럼 다시 돌아가죠
First of all, the specialist model calculates a number and then the frontier model calculates the number
먼저 전문 모델에서 숫자를 계산하고 그다음은 개척 모델에서 랙 검색을 통해 숫자를
with the Rag lookup and then the random forest model.
계산해요 그다음은 무작위 숲 모델이죠
And then the ensemble model.
앙상블 모델도요
And that goes back to the planning agent.
다 기획 담당자 책임이죠
And so you can read through all of this.
이걸 다 읽어보세요
And at the end of this it completed and it sent a push notification.
이게 끝나면 푸시 알림을 보내죠
And I did indeed get a push notification about this particular deal that it found, which was a certified
푸시 알림을 받았어요 어떤 거래에 관한 거였죠 재정비된 인증된 노트북이었어요
refurbished laptop boasting a 13th generation i5, which the estimate was $925 for that, which was
13세대 i5를 자랑하고 있었죠 추정 가격은 925달러였어요 560달러였으니
a very healthy discount to what it was going for at $560.
상당히 할인된 가격이죠
So there we have it.
자, 됐어요
That was the run of our agent framework running.
에이전트 프레임워크가 실행되고 있는 것이었고요
And yeah, it's incredibly satisfying to see that happening.
그런 모습을 보면 정말 만족스러워요
I love absolutely love watching it and could watch it all day.
보는 게 정말 좋아요 온종일 볼 수도 있어요
I have to say it's it's hugely enjoyable.
솔직히 정말 즐거워요
Look, I didn't even need to put that to bring that one out of the oven, because the one that we put
보세요, 오븐에서 꺼낼 때 이걸 꺼낼 필요도 없었어요 이미 오븐에
in the oven is now cooking up.
넣은 게 지금 익고 있거든요
You can see once modal is warmed up, it's quite fast in how it turns around the different things.
모듈이 워밍업이 되면 다양한 것들을 빠르게 전환할 수 있어요
So it's going through there.
여길 통과하는군요
It's come up with something.
뭔가 떠올랐어요
And of course, what it's proposing is different to what it proposed a moment ago.
물론 방금 제안한 것과 다른 내용이죠
And I just got the notification on my phone and no doubt on my watch.
방금 휴대폰 알림이 떴는데 시계에도 떴을 거예요
So we just watched we just saw the full framework running and me getting the notification.
방금 전체 프레임워크가 실행되는 걸 봤죠 제가 알림을 받는 것도요
And you can read through this trace and see how each of the agents are collaborating to solve this problem.
이 흔적을 읽어보면 각 요원이 이 문제를 해결하기 위해 어떻게 협력하는지 알 수 있죠
Um, and so all that remains for this is to make it really autonomous so that it's running all the time.
이제 남은 건 자율 주행이 가능하게 만드는 거예요
And while we're doing that, we might as well slap on a great UI because we know how to use gradio and
그걸 하는 동안 멋진 UI를 적용하는 게 좋겠죠 그러디오 사용법을 알고 그게 얼마나 좋은지
we know how good it is.
알거든요
And all of that is what we're going to do tomorrow.
그 모든 걸 내일 할 거예요
But for now, I'm going to let you, of course, enjoy this.
하지만 지금은 이 순간을 즐기게 해 줄게요
I do hope that you're running this a few times because it's so satisfying.
몇 번 더 해보세요 정말 만족스럽거든요
Honestly, I love it.
솔직히 마음에 들어요
Hope you're finding just as much enjoyment as me, and I will see you for the slides to wrap up the
여러분도 저만큼 즐거우시면 좋겠네요 오늘 마무리는 슬라이드에서 보여드릴게요